<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Career | Scribbles and Bits]]></title>
  <link href="http://derek.github.io/blog/blog/categories/career/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://derek.github.io/blog/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-17T18:13:40-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://derek.github.io/blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Derek Gathright]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leaving Yahoo]]></title>
    <link href="http://derek.github.io/blog/2013/on-leaving-yahoo/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-07T16:47:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://derek.github.io/blog/2013/on-leaving-yahoo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A week ago I walked out of Building E for the last time. There are a lot of emotions as I reflect back on everything that has happened over the last 4 years <a href="http://derek.io/blog/2009/im-a-yahoo">since I joined</a>, the jubilant successes, the lesson-learning failures, and everything in between. I have to think that in the end, it will likely go down as one of the more fun and rewarding periods of my life.</p>




<h2>Some highlights...</h2>




<ul>
<li>Attending, speaking, and mentoring hackers at <a href="http://derekgathright.com/resume/#conferences">27 conferences</a>. The YDN crew is world-class, and despite all the free food and nice benefits, working with them is one of the best perks of being an engineer at Yahoo. At least I think so. Special thanks to Anil, Havi, and Stacy for all their support at Hackdays, and helping organize SoCal meetups.</li>
<li>I feel fortunate to have been around for the beginning stages of what everyone hopes will be Yahoo’s "big turnaround". We probably won’t know for another 2 or 3 years if it will ultimately succeed, but the changes made in the first 18 months have been exciting to witness. While I don’t envision myself taking over a struggling Fortune 500 company anytime soon, learning some lessons for what it takes to turn that ship around been invaluable. Communicate, set goals, accomplish, repeat. Simple, right? We'll find out.</li>
<li>I also feel fortunate to have had the unique opportunity to work on <a href="http://yuilibrary.com/">a project</a> that reaches, what... 1/7th of the Earth's population in a given month? Kinda mindblowing when you think about it. And to top it off, you get to do it while working with a really talented and passionate group of people.</li>
<li>It was especially great being able to see the insides of how to effectively manage a large open-source project. Since YUI is on a never-ending quest to open up as much as possible, looking back on where it was in 2009 compared to now is pretty remarkable. Some of that praise should of course be given to Github, for producing such an amazing product for open-source organizations and letting developers focus on developing. The entire culture around open-source has evolved greatly in the last few years, and I think YUI has responded remarkably well.</li>
<li>Hacks! Especially ones with YQL. Between things like the <a href="https://github.com/yahoo/yql-executor">YQL Executor</a>, <a href="http://derek.io/blog/2010/how-to-secure-oauth-in-javascript/">Secure OAuth in JavaScript</a>, hacking YUI inside of YQL, SoCal Hackdays, Hacker Movie Nights, late-night scripting competitions with Dan Beam, and my projects from internal Hackdays, Yahoo absolutely cultivates the hacker mentality. I couldn't tell you if Paul Graham was right about Yahoo's <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/yahoo.html">dead hacker culture</a> in 1998, but it certainly doesn't apply in 2013. Let a thousand hacks bloom! (as one of my hack-discuss memos once said)</li>
<li>The Purple Kitten Tracker. One of these days, purple kittens will make an appearance in URLs, and it will be glorious.</li>
<li>Y! Sports Karaoke. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=izGwDsrQ1eQ">I'll just leave this here</a>.</li>
<li>But most of all, the biggest highlight was simply setting a career goal, <a href="http://derek.io/blog/2010/return-to-sunnyvale">accomplishing it</a>, then <a href="http://derek.io/blog/2011/joining-yui">again</a>.</li>
</ul>




<h2>To conclude...</h2>




<p>It was a pleasure to work with so many smart and passionate people, which was the entire reason <a href="http://derek.io/blog/2011/the-best-career-advice-youll-ever-get">why I joined Yahoo</a>. If you are the smartest person in the room and not the CEO, go find a smarter room. If you are working for a company that doesn’t believe in you, it’s time for a change. Ultimately, your career is about you, and the best way to succeed is to have the support of a company that can help you reach your goals. Yahoo gave me an immense amount of support over the years, and I'll always be grateful. So thanks to my managers Michael, Dan, Thomas, and Jenny.</p>




<h2>What’s Next?</h2>




<p>Believe it or not, in my four years at Yahoo I only took one vacation. So, I'm going to spend a few months off, Hawaii next week, travel more after that, hack on new projects, contribute to open-source, and eventually find my next adventure! If you are interested in speaking to me about opportunities, you can <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/derekgathright">connect with me on LinkedIn</a>, and find any other relevant links at <a href="http://derek.io/">derek.io</a>.</p>




<p>Well Yahoo... So long, and thanks for all the fish!</p>




<div align="center">
  <img height="300" src="http://i.imgur.com/rJVteIv.jpg" />
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Best Career Advice You'll Ever Get]]></title>
    <link href="http://derek.github.io/blog/2011/the-best-career-advice-youll-ever-get/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-06T21:02:34-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://derek.github.io/blog/2011/the-best-career-advice-youll-ever-get</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Huffington Post just posted an interview with Marissa Mayer (<a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/07/06/google-marissa-mayer-women-in-tech_n_891167.html"><em>&ldquo;Google Exec Marissa Mayer Explains Why There Aren&rsquo;t More Girl Geeks&rdquo;</em></a>) in which she explained why she chose Google over 13 other companies she had job offers from out of college.</p>

<blockquote><em>"Work with the smartest people you can find, do something you're not ready to do, find an environment in which you're very comfortable so you can find your voice, and work for someone who believes in you -- because when they believe in you, they'll invest in you."</em></blockquote>


<p>I couldn&rsquo;t agree more.  For some people, that&rsquo;s Google or Facebook.  For others, that is a startup.  For me, that encompasses every reason why I&rsquo;m at Yahoo.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Planting Seeds]]></title>
    <link href="http://derek.github.io/blog/2011/planting-seeds/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-07T15:20:18-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://derek.github.io/blog/2011/planting-seeds</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>6 years and 6 months ago I was a recent college grad, unemployed, and recently fired from my computer sales job.  I was horrible at sales.  Not because I&rsquo;m not social and can&rsquo;t communicate, but because I always viewed myself as being on the side of the customer, not the employer.  &ldquo;<em>No, you don&rsquo;t need that, it&rsquo;s twice as expensive as this model, and you won&rsquo;t use most of the features.  Here, this one is a better fit for you. Actually, you probably don&rsquo;t even need this at all.</em>&rdquo;</p>

<p>Needless to say, sales managers don&rsquo;t really like that attitude.</p>

<p>So as a 24 year old (f)unemployed person, how do you spend your time? Trying to sell a professional sports team, of course.</p>

<p>Alright, that statement deserves a little explanation.  If you know me, you know I&rsquo;m a huge soccer fan. I&rsquo;d been attending Kansas City Wizards games since Major League Soccer&rsquo;s inception (1996) and was very involved in the KC team&rsquo;s supporters group.  Well, a few days after I was given a pink slip, on Dec 9th, 2004 the Wizards ownership group announced they had pretty much given up hope on the team and were putting it up for sale.  That was pretty devastating for us fans.  We knew there was little chance someone was going to come in and buy an MLS team in Kansas City.  If they did, they were buying it to move to another city.  There wasn&rsquo;t much hope in keeping our team, but we weren&rsquo;t going to lose it without a fight.</p>

<p>Being without a job, I had more than enough time to take the initiative and get the ball rolling.  I registered our name (Heart of America Soccer Foundation), wrote forum posts, sent out emails, made phone calls, hosted a wiki for us to organize, etc&hellip;  It was a busy time for a lot of us.  Within a few weeks, we were having meetings, internally, with politicians, and with potential ownership groups.  Our goal was to make the city and fanbase as attractive as possible to anyone interested in making a significant investment in the team.  We of course weren&rsquo;t the ones selling the team, but we could make a pretty convincing argument that Kansas City was the right home for whoever was buying it.  It was a collective voice that needed to be heard.</p>

<p>While we organized &amp; communicated mostly online, early-on we were without a website, so that needed to change.  Wordpress of today would have been perfect for the task, but this was 2004, so it was pretty unknown at the time and certainly wasn&rsquo;t as robust as it is now. I had built a few web sites before, dabbled in PHP, HTML, and CSS, but had never built anything too special and certainly nothing professional appearing. However, that didn&rsquo;t discourage me, and I was excited for the challenge of learning how to build the site from scratch.  Luckily, we had a talented designer in the group, so all I had to do was the coding.  Off I went.</p>

<p>Because of how much fun I was having building the HASF website, I started to have the confidence that maybe I could turn my long-time programming hobby into a career. Within a few weeks, I had my first interview for a web developer position at a local startup.  During that interview, I was asked all the typical questions, some technical, and some non-technical.  I was doing ok.  Well, maybe. My lack of professional experience was pretty evident, cause I had none.  Towards the end I was asked, &ldquo;<em>Do you have a website you&rsquo;ve built that you could show us?</em>&rdquo;</p>

<p>Luckily&hellip;</p>

<p>&ldquo;<em>Sure, I just built one a few weeks ago</em>&rdquo;, and we pulled up <a href="http://hoasoccer.org">hoasoccer.org</a> on the projector.</p>

<p>I was pretty proud of it, and they could tell as I enthusiastically talked about all the things I wanted to eventually do with it.</p>

<p>Later that night, I got a phone call, and a job offer.  Accepted!</p>

<p>As I ventured into a new career, my involvement with HASF had to take a backseat.  Oh, I was still involved, but I just didn&rsquo;t have enough time to spend the majority of each day as the COO of a grassroots organization. At that point, more qualified individuals took leadership roles and did an amazing job.  It was a long process, but on August 31st, 2006, the team was finally sold to a local ownership group for $20 million.  Mission accomplished!</p>

<p>Well, mission accomplished as far as HASF was concerned.  There was still a massive uphill battle for the new owners to get a stadium built for the team, ensuring its long-term home is Kansas City.  Luckily for them, some of those heavily involved with HASF joined the new ownership group filling a variety of roles. It&rsquo;s a very talented, passionate group of individuals.  While I worked on building my career, they continued on the journey to build a world-class soccer stadium right in the heartland, in Kansas City.  I was rooting for them every step of the way.</p>

<p>At the same time, in 2007 I was working as a developer at an advertising agency, and not having very much fun there. Jeff, a friend from HASF, emailed me one day about a meeting with a family friend of his who was working on a startup.  We heard the pitch, and the challenge was exciting.  I was in the process of buying my first home, so leaving a steady job and going month-to-month contract at a web startup was a pretty dumb idea. My mom disliked it, can&rsquo;t blame her.  But, I took it, and had an extremely satisfying 2.5 years there.  It even directly led to the <a href="http://derek.io/blog/2009/im-a-yahoo/">next chapter</a> in my career.</p>

<p>Fast forward to today, a journey that started on Dec 9th, 2004 is going to conclude on June 9th, 2011 with that first game at <a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Livestrong_Sporting_Park">LIVESTRONG Sporting Park</a>, home of Sporting Kansas City (formerly Kansas City Wizards).  That&rsquo;s 2,374 days of hard work one group of people have done to accomplish something uniquely special. I now live in Los Angeles, but am making the trip back for the first game in the new stadium this week. For myself, it&rsquo;s going to be pretty amazing walking into that stadium for the first time.  There&rsquo;s a personal connection.  But I can&rsquo;t even imagine what it will be like for those people who have been involved with every step of the process.</p>

<p>It boggles my mind to think what I&rsquo;d be doing if I didn&rsquo;t wake up one day and decide I wanted to help save a sports team.  If I don&rsquo;t co-found a non-profit organization that had nothing to do with technology, I likely don&rsquo;t get that first programming job at a startup.  If I don&rsquo;t work at that startup where I learned what it takes to build the engineering side of a company, I don&rsquo;t get the experience to actually lead the next startup.  Well, that next one is what directly led to where I am today and the <a href="http://derek.io/blog/2011/joining-yui/">new position</a> I&rsquo;ll be starting in a few weeks.</p>

<p>The takeaway from this story is that you need to be driven by your passions.  This stadium&rsquo;s story very likely could have happened without my involvement early on.  But the fun part is, it did happen with my involvment.  When you are motivated by things that you love, you&rsquo;ll make awesome things happen. Continually plant seeds for for the future, because eventually some of those seeds will turn into trees.</p>

<p>You never know, someday one of those trees might look like this&hellip;</p>

<div align="center">
<img width="620" src="http://s89997654.onlinehome.us/screencaps/livestrongpark-20110607-193725.jpg">
<img width="620" src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5029/5766503395_0aaed7a194_b.jpg">
<img width="620" src="http://i.imgur.com/jxdSpZV.jpg">

Photo credits:
Facade: Ramsey Mohsen - <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/33161367@N04/5766503681/sizes/l/in/photostream/">Flickr</a> 
Grass: <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/33161367@N04/5766503395/sizes/l/in/photostream/">Flickr</a>

</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Joining YUI]]></title>
    <link href="http://derek.github.io/blog/2011/joining-yui/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-05T22:10:06-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://derek.github.io/blog/2011/joining-yui</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It seems like just yesterday I <a href="http://derek.io/blog/2009/im-a-yahoo/">accepted a position</a> with Yahoo and began a new adventure. These last 18 months have been an incredibly exciting time in my life, and am very thankful to have been given the opportunity. I can confidently say that Yahoo is -the- best place to work as a front-end engineer.</p>

<p>Well, the next chapter is about to begin.</p>

<p><img src="http://s89997654.onlinehome.us/screencaps/Twitter___%40Derek_Gathright__Exciting_day._Accepted_a_p_...-20110605-203607.jpg" alt="Tweet: Exciting day. Accepted a position with the YUI team at Yahoo. Yes, that means I'll be moving to NoCal. Watch out San Fran! I'm comin for ya." /></p>

<p><em>(Note: I&rsquo;ve since learned it is actually &ldquo;NorCal&rdquo;, not &ldquo;NoCal&rdquo;. Me = California noob.)</em></p>

<h2>What is YUI?</h2>


<p>YUI (mostly pronounced &ldquo;Y U I&rdquo;, sometimes &ldquo;Yooey&rdquo;) is an abbreviation for the <strong>Y</strong>ahoo <strong>U</strong>ser <strong>I</strong>nterface library. It&rsquo;s a project that began in 2005, and was open-sourced in 2006. It is primarily a JavaScript library, but also contains some CSS components as well (see: <a href="http://developer.yahoo.com/yui/grids/">Grids</a>, <a href="http://developer.yahoo.com/yui/reset/">Reset</a>). It is used extensively across just about every webpage Yahoo has, and it is popular externally as well.</p>

<p><a id="more"></a><a id="more-1030"></a></p>

<p>The reason we need JavaScript libraries is because web browsers have inconsistent implementations of the CSS &amp; ECMAScript (JavaScript) standards. Some browsers render something one way, while others do it in another way. We need to level the field and have a standard way to make stuff happen in the browser, so it&rsquo;s the job of the library to abstract out all the differences and give developers a sane way to make your browser do something.</p>

<p>You can read more about the concept on Wikipedia: <a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/JavaScript_library">JavaScript Library</a>.</p>

<h2>Why is YUI awesome?</h2>


<p>Early on in my time at Yahoo, it became pretty clear to me that at some point in my career, I wanted to work for the YUI team. Here&rsquo;s why&hellip;</p>

<ul>
    <li>It's an open-source project with a very liberal BSD license. Yay!</li>
    <li>It's widely used both inside of Yahoo, and externally as well.</li>
    <li>It's a very exciting time for JavaScript as it invades the server (thanks to projects like <a href="http://nodejs.org">Node.js</a>) and YUI runs amazingly well in a server environment. Better than any other full-featured JS library.</li>
    <li>YUI's module system is one of the best out there. It allows you to create lean, fast, and portable applications.</li>
    <li>YUI is way more than just a DOM manipulation library, it is a platform for JavaScript applications. For that reason, I think YUI is in a great position to really make an impact as JavaScript is used in new &amp; innovative ways.</li>
    <li>It's one of the most important projects Yahoo is working on and gets immense support from within the company. It even has its own <a href="http://yuilibrary.com/yuiconf2010/">conference</a>.</li>
    <li>The YUI team and the YUI community are equals. The YUI Gallery allows anyone to contribute to the collection of modules YUI can use, and we'll even host the code for you.</li>
    <li>YUI has some of the brightest, and most passionate people in the industry working on the project. It's an honor to be considered among them.</li>
</ul>


<p>If you read my post on <a href="http://derek.io/blog/2011/the-engineer/">the mentality of the engineer</a>, you&rsquo;ll know that I really appreciate a good challenge. Well, this is going to be one of the funnest, most exciting challenges of my career thus far. As I listened to the FLOSS Weekly podcast <a href="http://twit.tv/floss23">episode on YUI</a> back in 2008, if you told me I&rsquo;d one day be working on that project, I would have laughed in your face.</p>

<p>I have a ways to go before I feel I&rsquo;m at the level a YUI'er should be, but I can&rsquo;t wait to get started.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Engineer]]></title>
    <link href="http://derek.github.io/blog/2011/the-engineer/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-30T18:00:46-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://derek.github.io/blog/2011/the-engineer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>According to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Engineering">Wikipedia</a>, Engineering is&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><em>"...the discipline, art and profession of acquiring and applying scientific, mathematical, economic, social, and practical knowledge to design and build structures, machines, devices, systems, materials and processes that safely realize solutions to the needs of society."</em></blockquote>


<p>This morning I was watching <a href="http://news.cnet.com/8301-13577_3-20023018-36.html">Carol Bartz&rsquo;s interview</a> at the Web 2.0 Summit, and John Battelle asked her the question about acquiring engineering talent in the software/web world. When he asked that question, I stopped what I was doing and focused on the conversation because it&rsquo;s important to me that our CEO understands what motivates us. If she doesn&rsquo;t &ldquo;get&rdquo; it, then the company has a serious problem. Here was her answer:</p>

<p>&ldquo;<em>[Engineers] want a really interesting job to do, they want to have the tools to do it, they want to work on large data sets and large problems, and [Yahoo] has that.</em>&rdquo;</p>

<p>Exactly what I wanted to here. And it&rsquo;s not just lip-service, there is really awesome stuff we&rsquo;re working on at the moment, things that haven&rsquo;t been done elsewhere, so it is clear she does get it.</p>

<p>Then, a theme began to emerge for the day. A friend that works in developer relations at HP/Palm tweeted&hellip;</p>

<p><a id="more"></a><a id="more-966"></a></p>

<p><img title="@adora: One of my greatest pleasures in life is giving developers interesting problems to solve" src="http://s89997654.onlinehome.us/screencaps/skitched-20101116-223758.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>And that&rsquo;s what makes <a href="http://twitter.com/adora">Lisa</a> great at what she does, she understands developers very well. She knows what makes us tick.</p>

<p>I work with an engineer (<a href="http://twitter.com/danbeam">@danbeam</a>) is so compulsive with solving problems that sometimes just to mess with him I&rsquo;ll say &ldquo;<em>I bet you can&rsquo;t figure this out</em>.&rdquo; I know that after 30 seconds of resisting, he has no choice but to drop everything and focus on solving it. Seriously, it works every time, it&rsquo;s pretty funny. We once spent hours battling back &amp; forth trying to generate the shortest shell script that will output every Friday the 13th. Why? Because it was Friday the 13th and we were curious. (Solution: <em>echo -e {$((2e5)).1}13\n|date -f-|grep ^F</em>)</p>

<p>I am obviously not immune to it myself. Recently, a friend sent me a link to the <a href="http://seatgeek.com/blog/hiring/henceforth-all-job-applicants-must-hack-into-our-backend">SeatGeek applicant hacking challenge</a>, I had no choice but to drop what I was doing and &ldquo;hack&rdquo; into the system even though I&rsquo;m happily employed. 15 minutes later, mission accomplished, back to work. It was fun for a few minutes, and I learned a couple things. (Tip: Try using nothing but cURL. Using a browser is cheating)</p>

<p>Solving these little problems is what keeps the engineer occupied. It is our form of entertainment. But if you are working with engineers, you don&rsquo;t want them to simply be entertained, you want them to be inspired. You want them so full of determination that they&rsquo;ll stop at nothing to figure out a solution. How do you do that? Give them something that isn&rsquo;t possible. That&rsquo;s like a mother telling her 13 year old son he can&rsquo;t do something. Oh yeah? Watch. (sorry mom!)</p>

<p>For instance, last year I wanted to figure out the best method to do OAuth using nothing but client-side JavaScript. It can&rsquo;t actually be impossible to do, can it? After a few weeks of hacking around, I came up with a solution and wrote a post about it, <a href="http://derek.io/blog/2010/how-to-secure-oauth-in-javascript/">How-to: Secure OAuth in JavaScript</a>. Yeah, it is using a proxy (YQL), but my code is all JS and I can host it anywhere. Close enough.</p>

<p>There was little practical reason for doing it, other than I just wondered how it could be done. There is a lot to learn by challenging yourself to do something you don&rsquo;t know how to do. The biggest lesson I learned from that project was to quit trying to coerce a library into doing something for you it wasn&rsquo;t intended to do. It&rsquo;s usually quicker to sack up, read the spec, and write a solution yourself. Me &amp; the <a href="http://oauth.net/core/1.0/">OAuth 1.0 spec</a> are like best buddies now.</p>

<p>Anyways, later on that same day, yet another relevant tweet rolled across my timeline&hellip;</p>

<p><img title="@BeOurGuestMike: #nasatweetup shows me each and every day how important it is to share with my students the passion of doing the once " src="http://s89997654.onlinehome.us/screencaps/Twitter___%40Mike_Rahlmann__%23nasatweetup_shows_me_each_...-20101116-224559.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>That, is an excellent teacher. I&rsquo;m a huge science nerd, and the NASA tweet reminded me of my favorite scene from Apollo 13. Yes, I&rsquo;m so nerdy that the scene where the engineers save the day is my favorite. In it, the crippled Lunar Module is flying back to Earth when engineers determine that the astronauts may soon die of carbon dioxide poisoning unless they devise a solution.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the clip&hellip;</p>

<iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/Z3csfLkMJT4" frameborder="0" width="560" height="349"></iframe>


<p>Those are the moments the engineer lives for. Solving interesting problems keep us occupied. Solving impossible problems is why we’re engineers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
